Alright, we're on ערכין דף כ"א, Erchin Daf Chaf Aleph, starting from
the משנה. Mishnah. We're starting a new topic today. We are looking
at when the בית דין Beis Din is permitted to confiscate property
in order to make you pay your obligations.
Your obligations, specifically in terms of this משנה, Mishnah, your obligations to
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Conflict of interest a little bit, no? Like the rabbis and the
temple always has the upper hand.
Yeah, I mean, I don't know if it's really because it's the
בית דין Beis Din and the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. I don't
know if the rabbis and the כהנים Kohanim always got along, so
it may not be, but
so the משנה Mishnah starts, חייבי ערכין ממשכנין אותן. Chayvei Erchin Memashkenin
Osan.
So one who is liable for ערכין, Erchin, and that's our connection
to the previous סוגיא Sugya in this פרק, Perek, so one who
has taken an ערך Erach on themselves, so we can be ממשכן
Memashken from משכון, Mashkon, collateral, we can confiscate property as collateral until
they pay the ערך Erach that they owe. חייבי חטאות ואשמות, Chayvei
Chataos Vaashamos, however, if you're liable for a קרבן חטאת Korban Chatas
or for a קרבן אשם, Korban Asham, אין ממשכנין אותן, Ein Memashkenin
Osan, we don't confiscate property.
Why not? We'll talk about it.
The גמרא Gemara will imply it, רש"י Rashi talks about it more
explicitly.
The basic rule seems to be anytime you have something to benefit
from paying your obligation, we assume you'll do it on your own,
and anytime it's just an obligation that you're not really benefiting from
any other way, then we're afraid you won't and we confiscate the
property to make you do it. So the חטאת Chatas and the
אשם, Asham, since they're coming for a specific sin that you need
כפרה Kapparah for, we assume that you're not going to try and
get out of it and you'll give the קרבן Korban on your
own,
as opposed to the ערך, Erach, which was completely voluntary, so we're
worried that you might not.
So it would be the same thing for נדרים Nedarim then, right?
If I took a נדר. Neder.
Right, ערכין Erchin is not in distinction to נדרים, Nedarim, that's just
the example that we start with here.
But you would think
the
opposite, because you're volunteering, you really want to do it. Nobody's making
you, you want to, whereas if you're obligated, like when you have
to pay a parking fine, who wants to do it? You put
it off.
Right, I hear the argument. There is definitely a logic to say
that what you voluntarily got yourself into, you want to do,
but the
משנה Mishnah
is assuming basically the rule is anytime unless you have something to
benefit from it as well, you might not.
Also, the אשם Asham is for atonement, right?
Yeah, the אשם Asham and the
חטאת, Chatas, that may be a deeper motivation, the atonement, than say
you just made a, say, you know, I'm contributing to something.
Right, that's exactly what the משנה Mishnah is assuming.
You can see it either way.
Right.
חייבי עולות ושלמים, Chayvei Olos Ushlamim,
so if you have to bring a קרבן עולה Korban Olah or
a קרבן שלמים, Korban Shelamim, presumably either because it's one of the
situations where the תורה Torah requires you to bring an עולה Olah
or a שלמים, Shelamim, or because you voluntarily.
The required one would be a little bit tough based on what
you just said.
No, but meaning if it's required without giving you something in return,
then we're worried that you might not want to do it. It's
specifically the חטאת Chatas that gives you כפרה Kapparah that.
The עולה Olah also has מכפר Mechaper on ביטול עשה. Bitul Aseh.
Right, so רש"י Rashi actually asks that.
רש"י Rashi on the משנה, Mishnah, עולות ושלמים אף על גב דשלמים
מכפרת עשה, Olos Ushlamim Af Al Gav Deshlamim Mechaperes Aseh, even though
the עולה Olah and the שלמים, Shelamim, רש"י Rashi just says שלמים,
Shelamim, right, so
צריך לומר, Tzarich Lomar,
right,
yeah, probably should be עולה Olah in the גירסא. Girsa. So even
though the עולה Olah does give כפרה Kapparah for ביטול עשה, Bitul
Aseh, for not fulfilling a positive commandment, הואיל ולא חובה היא עליה
לא חשיב לה כפרה. Hoil Velo Chova Hi Aleha Lo Chashiv Lah
Kapparah. Because it's not a כפרה Kapparah that you're strictly required to
get, the משנה Mishnah doesn't consider it כפרה Kapparah in this case.
So it's a חובה Chova but not a כפרה, Kapparah, like the
עולת ראייה Olas Re'iyah then they would be ממשכן Mashken on you
because you don't get anything out of it? Or you do because
I mean.
So the גמרא Gemara actually is not going to discuss עולת ראייה,
Olas Re'iyah, but the גמרא Gemara will discuss there are certain exceptions
to the general rules presented in the משנה. Mishnah.
So where they say getting you part of the קרבן Korban or
what does that matter?
So the only example we've seen so far is getting כפרה, Kapparah,
you get atonement for your sin when you bring the חטאת Chatas
or the אשם.
Asham.
In the גמרא, Gemara, we'll see some other benefits as well.
I see, I wonder what would be considered, what would be the
difference.
Right.
So then the משנה Mishnah says, אף על פי שאין מתכפר לו
עד שירצה. Af Al Pi She'ein Miskafer Lo Ad Sheyirtzeh.
So even though, even though you won't get, and now we are
talking about the כפרה Kapparah from the עולה Olah
for not fulfilling a positive commandment, so even though you're not going
to
get
that
atonement... However, what can we do? כופין אותו עד שיאמר רוצה אני.
kofin oto ad she'yomar rotzeh ani. The בית דין Beit Din can
force him until he says, "I want to bring it."
Right.
And then the משנה Mishna just sticks in parenthetically, וכן אתה אומר
בגיטי נשים כופין אותו עד שיאמר רוצה אני. ve'chen ata omer be'gittei
nashim kofin oto ad she'yomar rotzeh ani. So this, by the way,
it's not really related to the rest of the משנה Mishna at
all, is the same, is the same דין din by divorce. Anytime
the בית דין Beit Din rules that a man is obligated to
divorce his wife, even though a divorce can't be forced, the בית
דין Beit Din can coerce him until he says, "I want to
do it."
Then they say it's a גט מעושה, get me'useh, it's not כשר.
kosher. They do, you know.
No, if the בית דין, Beit Din, if anyone else but בית
דין Beit Din forces him, it's a גט מעושה. get me'useh. If
בית דין Beit Din forces him but he doesn't say the words
"I want to give it of my own free will," then it's
a גט מעושה. get me'useh. But if בית דין Beit Din forces
him and he says "I want to give it of my own
free will," then it's no longer a גט מעושה. get me'useh.
Unfortunately, בתי דין Batei Din don't really have much power of forcing
people today, but
they don't in the גולה, Golah, but in ישראל Yisrael they have
plenty of power.
Yes, in ישראל. Yisrael. The problem is in America. In America, the
בתי דין Batei Din have no power, and in ישראל Yisrael they
have the power and don't use it.
In America, they... it's for another discussion. They have a lot of
psychological power over people who need a גט. get.
And the responsible בתי דין Batei Din that are doing are using
that to the best of their ability.
There's no such thing.
But that's
not our conversation.
I know.
אמר רב פפא. Amar Rav Pappa. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר
רב פפא פעמים שחייבי חטאות ממשכנין אותם.
Amar Rav
Pappa pe'amim she'chayavei chata'ot memashkenin otam.
So רב פפא Rav Pappa says there are exceptions to our משנה.
Mishna. There are times when even someone who has to bring a
חטאת, chatat, we can still, we can still confiscate property. חייבי עולות
אין ממשכנין אותם. Chayavei olot ein memashkenin otam. And also there are
times when someone is obligated to bring an עולה olah and nevertheless
we don't confiscate property. So what are the examples of this? חייבי
חטאות ממשכנין אותן בחטאת נזיר. Chayavei chata'ot memashkenin otan be'chatat nazir. So
the case where, the case where you would
confiscate property for a חטאת chatat is by the חטאת chatat that
a נזיר nazir has to bring. A נזיר nazir has to bring
three קרבנות korbanot when he ends or she ends the נזירות. nezirut.
One is a חטאת, chatat, one is an עולה, olah, one is
a שלמים. shelamim. And this is, I mean,
it makes sense that this one is an exception because this is
a חטאת chatat which isn't coming on any particular sin,
and therefore there isn't,
there isn't כפרה, kapparah, there isn't atonement that he's getting from it.
There is something else he's getting from it. He's getting the right
to drink wine again, to go to cemeteries again. So that's, that's
another example of something that you're getting from a קרבן. korban. But
why, why don't we confiscate property, I mean rather why do we
confiscate property even though he is getting that from it? So דכיון
דאמר מר אם גילח על אחת משלשתן יצא ואם נזרק עליו אחד
מן הדמים הותר הנזיר לשתות יין ולטמא למתים.
de'keivan de'amar mar im gile'ach al achat mi'shloshtan yatza ve'im nizrak alav
echad min
ha'damim hutar ha'nazir lishtot yayin u'letamei le'metim. ופשיע ולא מייתי. u'pashia velo
mayti.
Right. ופשיע ולא מייתי. u'pashia velo mayti.
So we're worried that since he doesn't actually have to bring all
three קרבנות korbanot to get the right to drink wine or go
to cemeteries, if on the, he can bring the three in any
order and on the first one he brings, as soon as he's
shaved off his head and the blood of the קרבן korban has
been, has been זריקה zerika has been done on the מזבח, mizbe'ach,
the blood has been sprinkled on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, as soon as
that happens on any one of them, he retains, he gets back
his right to drink wine and to come in contact with the
dead.
And then the other two are just his obligation to bring the
other two, but he's not getting anything from them anymore. So therefore
we're worried ופשיע ולא מייתי u'pashia velo mayti that he will be
negligent and not bring them. And therefore we do confiscate property even
for that חטאת.
chatat. Well, is it only if there's an indication he's not going
to do it? I mean, are we saying from the very beginning
we're ממשכן memashken you because we assume you're not going to bring
it?
I mean, it makes sense to me that we don't
necessarily go and confiscate property right away. It's, you know, if he
hasn't brought it after, you know, X time, whatever, I don't know
what the time is that we'd confiscate property,
but I don't know if that ever gets discussed anywhere. I have
no idea. Nowhere I've come across. Yeah.
So חייבי עולות
אין ממשכנין אותן. chayavei olot ein memashkenin otan. So what's the case
of an עולה olah that we don't confiscate property for? So the
גמרא Gemara is first going to suggest and then reject and then
give another answer. But we're first going to suggest עולת יולדת. olat
yoledet. So
a woman who just gave birth has to bring two קרבנות. korbanot.
She brings an עולה olah and a חטאת. chatat.
Again, this is, this is another חטאת chatat just like the חטאת
נזיר chatat nazir that isn't coming on a sin, it's not bringing
atonement.
So the גמרא Gemara is assuming as follows. The חטאת chatas we
don't confiscate property for because she's going to bring because
she wants to be able to eat sacrifices. The עולה olah has
to be brought before the חטאת. chatas. And since since she can't
bring the חטאת chatas until until she brings the עולה olah and
the חטאת chatas she wants to bring because she wants to be
able to eat sacrifices, therefore she's going to bring the עולה olah
as well and we don't have to confiscate property. And that's the
גמרא's Gemara הוה אמינא, havamina, that's what we're assuming. Then the גמרא
Gemara asks, מאי ניהו? mai nihu? So essentially why are you assuming
this? Why why
are
you assuming that the עולה olah has to be brought before the
חטאת? chatas? דאקדמיה קרא? de-akdamei kra? Because it comes first in the
פסוק? pasuk? The the פסוק pasuk by יולדת yoledet lists the עולה
olah and then the חטאת. chatas. והאמר רבא, ve-hamar Rava, למקרא הקדימה
הכתוב. le-mikra hikdima hakatuv. רבא Rava
didn't didn't רבא Rava tell us the only reason the תורה Torah
listed עולה olah first is because the תורה Torah wanted us to
read it first? But actually they can be brought in any order.
And and therefore she could bring the חטאת chatas first and have
the right to have the right to eat קדשים, kodshim, to eat
sacrifices right away. And then
the
עולה olah is just an obligation that she isn't gaining anything from,
we'd have to worry that she wouldn't bring the עולה olah and
therefore we ought to be able to confiscate property from it. So
גמרא Gemara says, you're right, there's a different example of an עולה
olah there's a different example of an עולה olah that you don't
have to confiscate property for. אלא, ella, בעולת מצורע. be-olat metzora. We're
talking about the עולה olah of a מצורע. metzora. So a מצורע
metzora has to bring three קרבנות korbanos and a מצורע metzora brings
an אשם, asham, brings a חטאת, chatas, and brings an עולה. olah.
And why don't we confiscate property for the עולת מצורע? olat metzora?
דתניא de-tanya רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יהודה בן ברקא אומר. Rabbi
Yishmael beno shel Rabbi Yehuda ben Beroka omer. So we have a
ברייתא, braisa, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael the son of רבי יהודה בן
ברקא Rabbi Yehuda ben Beroka says, כשם שחטאתו ואשמו עכבתו כך עולתו
עכבתו. keshem she-chatato ve-ashamo ikavto, kach olato ikavto.
So the מצורע metzora has something to gain, he he is let
he is let back into the camp, he's no longer he's no
longer טמא. tamei. And
and the ברייתא braisa tells us that actually he doesn't get any
of these until he brings all three. He needs the חטאת chatas
and the אשם asham and the עולה. olah. And therefore since he
needs to bring all three to get all his full rights back,
we're not worried that he's not going to bring the עולה. olah.
Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara moves on to the next bit in the משנה. Mishnah.
Yes?
I just I mean my thoughts, so first time I've ever thought
of this whole context of being forced to bring what you would
think, you know, I always thought of in terms of these are
obligations and we're doing it for ourselves. But here it's almost as
if they have an alter- I mean it sounds ridiculous, but as
if they have an ulterior motive to force these people to do
this. Are they doing it for these people's own good? Or are
they doing it because they want to have the this for their
use in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you know what I mean?
Like a conflict of interest.
I mean I don't know what they mean for their use. I
mean a חטאת chatas maybe because you mean because the כהנים kohanim
eat, but the חטאת chatas we don't.
No, but there is a concept of the מזבח, mizbeach, you know,
having
right, meaning for our just strictly for our religious needs that we
want to have animals on the altar? Yeah, maybe. I mean it's
also a financial debt. If you if you owe money to the
temple, the temple has the right to collect the money.
So they keep track of who is a מצורע metzora every time
a woman gives birth, they're going to keep track and come and
force you
to fulfill your obligation?
I assume I don't know what kind of record system they had,
but yeah. Yeah.
I mean any people's watching.
I
mean
any institution keeps tracks of keeps track of debts that they're owed,
so yeah, I don't see why not.
And what I need to make the distinction between, you know, I
was always looking at the offerings as something coming from myself, yeah,
for our own good. And here it's almost as if it's more
of a societal obligation, you know, that has to do with financial.
Right, so I mean I think both are true. Both are true.
One, it is a financial debt, they have a right to collect
their financial debts and
and two,
you know, once once you have an obligation it's now, you know,
it's for your own good, for your own, you know, for your
soul, for your relationship with God that you should, you know, fulfill
your obligation. So just like I mean in this is not what
we're learning now but in מסכת סנהדרין, Masechet Sanhedrin, so we talk
about where where the בית דין Beis Din can force people to
fulfill מצוות mitzvot and when not.
So it's, you know, if I were to if I were to
promise a person a gift, yeah,
would that have the same would there be the same level of
obligation for me to give
it?
I would think so.
But you know, even with this, it doesn't necessarily mean that they're
keeping track of everybody. It could be if like they happened to
have found out, you know, then they would maybe enforce this. It
might be one of these things that's sort of like on the
books is like, you know, this is what our procedure officially would
be were we to know about it, but it may not be
like, you know, looking around sort of like with פרעה, Paro, you
know, keeping track of when the women were together with their husbands
so they can count, you know, till the baby's born. It may
not be at the same level of intrusiveness on a day-to-day basis.
But before they're even counting, you could argue and say that there's
something that's very important.
Right. But again, yeah, I mean, I think it's not strictly financial.
There are both aspects and I don't know really necessarily which one
they're trying to emphasize here. But yeah, A is a financial debt
and B is a מצווה, mitzvah, and the בית דין Beit Din
has the right to coerce for both things. So it's hard to
tell exactly necessarily which one we're talking about. Alright,
so the משנה Mishnah
said, אף על פי שאין מתכפר עד שיתרצה, Af al pi she'ein
mitkaper ad she'yitratzeh,
so even though you can't get the atonement until you want to
do it of your own free
will.
Excuse me.
So the גמרא Gemara quotes a ברייתא: Baraita: תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan:
יקריב אותו. Yakriv oto.
The פסוק, pasuk, which the whole פסוק pasuk says, אם עלה קרבנו
מן הבקר זכר תמים יקריבנו אל פתח אהל מועד יקריב אתו, Im
olah korbano min habakar zachar tamim yakrivenu el petach ohel moed yakriv
oto, לרצונו
לפני ה'. Lirtzono lifnei Hashem. The גמרא Gemara is going to get
to that part. But right now we're focusing on if you're bringing
an עולה, olah, you offer it up at the
entrance of the Tent of Meeting, at the entrance of the משכן
Mishkan or the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So the word יקריב אותו
yakriv oto מלמד שכופין אותו, melamed she'kofin oto, that it has to
be offered no matter what, I think is how they're reading the
פסוק, pasuk, and therefore that teaches that we can apply pressure, that
we can coerce. יכול בעל כרחו? Yachol b'al korcho? I might have
thought even completely against his will? תלמוד לומר לרצונו. Talmud lomar: Lirtzono.
The פסוק pasuk says it has to be according to his will.
הא כיצד? Ha keitzad?
What? In his mind or his will, not the actual giving of
the קרבן? korban?
No,
the actual giving of the קרבן. korban. Once he pledged it already,
then yes, we are talking about the actual giving of the קרבן
korban now.
We're not talking about— But who does he verbalize this to? Does
he verbalize it to a witness? As you said before, if he
verbalizes it to a witness, then it's up against him. But if
he internalizes or
says nothing— Wait, I mean, he has to come and bring the
animal himself and say, "This is my קרבן." korban. We can't just
go and take an animal and offer it up on his behalf.
But who do I designate if I'm giving it to him? I
mean, do I have to say I'm going to give it to—
Do people have to be witnesses for
my gift or my debt? I mean, it's in the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, there's a lot of people around, so—
No, he means to get to the point where they're going to
be כופין kofin you.
Oh, yeah, of course, of course there have to be witnesses. If
there are no witnesses, then they have
no— For my, for
my flock, I designate— Yeah, I mean, if there are no witnesses,
then they have no way of knowing what נדר neder you made.
So once it's a collective comes from wherever it is.
Right.
Yeah, no, anything בית דין Beit Din does, they need witnesses for.
Yeah.
That's if the woman gave birth, then it's—and she's חייב, chayav, we
said they can force her, right?
Yes, I mean, but we have to know she gave birth. If
she's denying that she gave birth, then of course we can't force
her unless we have witnesses to the fact. She
had the
baby, she's got some snot on her. Right.
If she—right, if you admit, right, if you admit on your own
that you owe it, then we don't need witnesses. That's true. If
she says, "I don't know, I adopted this baby," and we don't
have witnesses that she gave birth to it, then she doesn't owe
anything because we have no way of proving it.
Right,
so הא כיצד? ha keitzad? So what's the case where we can
force, but it's still in his will? כופין אותו עד שיאמר רוצה
אני. Kofin oto ad she'yomar rotzeh ani. So we apply the pressure
until he says, "I want to do
it."
So אמר שמואל: Amar Shmuel:
עולה צריכה דעת שנאמר לרצונו. Olah tzricha da'at, shene'emar lirtzono. So שמואל
Shmuel says a קרבן עולה korban olah needs
to have your will to give it because the פסוק pasuk says
according to his will.
Is this any different than what we just said?
That's the גמרא's Gemara question. מאי קמשמע לן? Mai kamashma lan?
What's שמואל Shmuel coming to teach us? תנינא: Tenina: אף על פי
שאין מתכפר לו עד שיתרצה שנאמר לרצונו. Af al pi she'ein mitkaper
lo ad she'yitratzeh shene'emar lirtzono. The משנה Mishnah already taught us he
doesn't get the atonement until he wants to bring it because the
פסוק pasuk says according to his will. So
the גמרא Gemara says: לא צריכא. Lo tzricha. We actually need שמואל's
Shmuel statement. What's he coming to teach us? דאפריש ליה חבריה. D'parish
lei chavrei.
Because someone else is donating the animal for his קרבן.
korban. מהו דתימא? Mahu d'teima? What would I have thought? כי בעינן
דעת
מדידיה אבל מדחבריה לא. Ki ba'inan da'at mididei, aval midechavrei lo. I
might have thought I only need his consent if it's his animal
because he doesn't necessarily want to consent because he's losing an animal.
On the other hand, if it's someone else's animal, who would ever
say no to it? He's not losing anything.
Meaning I'm bringing an עולה olah on your behalf.
I—
Yeah, I pledged an עולה Olah and you say, "Here, I'm going
to donate this cow, this sheep from my, from my flock to
fulfill your obligation."
So it sounds like we need both, we need the דעת Da'at
of both, right? Mine and yours.
Well, yeah, I mean if it's your דעת, Da'at, it's stealing, right?
That's what they're saying, right?
Yeah.
You're just transferring it over, though. Right.
So I might have thought that if it's someone else's, if it's
someone else that's donating the animal, you don't need explicit, you don't
need explicit consent because he's not losing anything. קא משמע לן. Ka
Mashma Lan. So שמואל Shmuel comes to teach us, זימנין דלא ניחא
ליה לכפורי במידי דלאו דידיה. Zimnin delo nicha leih lechapurei bemidi delav
dideih. No, there are some people, there are some times when people
don't want to get atonement from something that wasn't theirs. And therefore
שמואל Shmuel teaches us even in that case we
need the consent of
all parties involved.
Yeah. Thank you. Okay, פשיטא. Pshita. So the גמרא Gemara is going
to bring a ברייתא Braita to challenge שמואל. Shmuel. חטאתו ואשמו של
פלוני עלי. Chatato ve'ashamo shel ploni alai.
So if someone pledges to give an animal to fulfill the obligation
of the חטאת Chatat or the אשם Asham of another person, לדעת
יצא, Leda'at yatza,
if it's with the consent, if he informs the other person and
they agree to it, if it's with the consent of the other
person, then they fulfill their obligation. שלא לדעת לא יצא, Shelo leda'at
lo yatza, if the other person doesn't know or doesn't agree to
it, then the obligation is not fulfilled. However, and here's where the
challenge is going to be, עולתו ושלמיו של פלוני עלי, Olato ushlamav
shel ploni alai, however, if you pledge an animal to fulfill
the obligation of another person for an עולה Olah or for a
שלמים, Shlamim, עולתו ושלמיו של פלוני עלי, Olato ushlamav shel ploni alai,
בין לדעת בין שלא לדעת יצא. Bein leda'at bein shelo leda'at yatza.
So in that case, whether or not they know about it, whether
or not they consent to it,
they've fulfilled their obligation. So that seems to challenge שמואל Shmuel who
said an עולה Olah requires consent as well.
So אמר לך שמואל, Amar lach Shmuel, so what would שמואל Shmuel
say back to you? כי תניא ההיא בשעת כפרה. Ki tanya hahi
bish'at kapara. דאיכא בשעת הפרשה. De'ika bish'at hafrasha. That
ברייתא Braita is talking about when the animal is actually being offered,
when it's being slaughtered in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. And there
you don't need to give explicit consent, you don't even need to
know exactly when it's going on. Why? דאיכא בשעת הפרשה, De'ika bish'at
hafrasha, because you already gave your consent at the time that the
animal was designated. כי קאמינא, Ki ka'amina,
שמואל Shmuel would say, when I said, כי קאמינא אנא, Ki ka'amina
ana, when I said my statement that it requires consent, בשעת הפרשה,
Bish'at hafrasha, that's at the time you designate the animal. And the
גמרא Gemara says, ופליגא דעולא. Upliga de'Ula.
שמואל Shmuel argues on
עולא. Ula. דאמר עולא, De'amar Ula, because we have this statement from
עולא. Ula. עולא Ula said, לא חלקו בין חטאת לעולה. Lo chilku
bein chatat le'olah. The only distinction that our ברייתא Braita was making
between a חטאת Chatat and an עולה, Olah, אלא שחטאת צריכה דעת
בשעת הפרשה ועולה אין צריכה דעת בשעת הפרשה. Ela shechatat tzricha da'at
bish'at hafrasha ve'olah ein tzricha da'at bish'at hafrasha.
So
עולא Ula says the ברייתא Braita was specifically distinguishing between the time
of, at the time of designation, that a חטאת Chatat needs consent
at the time of designation and an עולה Olah does not need
consent at the time of designation. אבל בשעת כפרה, Aval bish'at kapara,
but at the time it's being offered, at the time they're actually
doing the sacrifice, אידי ואידי לדעת יצא שלא לדעת לא יצא. Idi
ve'idi leda'at yatza shelo leda'at lo yatza. Both the חטאת Chatat and
the עולה Olah
with consent the obligation is fulfilled and without consent it's not fulfilled.
But we learned זבחים, Zevachim, no one said that עולה Olah needs
דעת, Da'at, right? It was only, it was only the, it was
only the, you know, חטאת אשם Chatat Asham perhaps. You remember we
had the whole מחלוקת? Machloket? It was
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who,
it's been a long time since we did זבחים, Zevachim, I don't
really remember it so well.
But שמואל Shmuel definitely says here עולה Olah needs דעת. Da'at.
And in fact עולא Ula seems to agree, at least בשעת כפרה.
Bish'at kapara.
They're the exact reverse of each other. שמואל Shmuel says an עולה
Olah needs דעת Da'at
בשעת הפרשה Bish'at hafrasha when it's being designated and it doesn't need
it בשעת כפרה Bish'at kapara when it's being offered. And עולא Ula
says, and עולא Ula says the reverse, it does not need it
בשעת הפרשה Bish'at hafrasha when it's being designated, it does need it
בשעת כפרה Bish'at kapara when it's being offered.
Right, and my question was I didn't remember that, you know, because
we had the whole thing about the כהנים, Kohanim, you know, like
they can generally have mind just whatever it is as long as
they're not having mind like a wrong thing, you know what I
mean? Like in absence of דעת. Da'at. But we said for חטאת
Chatat though it needs, since it's for a specific person, then it
does need to have דעת. Da'at. And then for, and then there
was a מחלוקת Machloket whether you extend that to אשם. Asham. But
no one was extending that to עולה Olah though.
But that was, I mean, no, I mean, that's, there are two
separate questions, remember from that, from the first משנה Mishna in זבחים.
Zevachim. There's, you can have the קרבן Korban be כשר Kasher of,
you know, it's a good קרבן, Korban, you could bring it on
the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, the כהנים Kohanim could eat the meat, whatever, but
nevertheless it doesn't fulfill the person's obligation. So that's what we're talking
about here. We're not saying it's an invalid קרבן, Korban, we're saying,
we're saying the person's obligation isn't fulfilled. Yeah, exactly.
Does the person have to I did such and such a sin
and therefore I'm giving a קרבן, korban, or that just as an
owner? What is the meaning by that, that he is going through
some transformation by giving an animal?
And I mean just the implication from the משנה Mishnah is it's
just רוצה אני, rotzeh ani, I want to bring this קרבן. korban.
But he doesn't have to verbalize for what fill in the blank?
No. So maybe that would be different because then you might have
switched the, you know, man it's just a routine thing, I'm giving
it because I have extra sheep, but if it's supposed to be
tied in with a,
you know, with a sin or whatever.
Right, but you know what you need atonement for, God knows what
you need atonement for, the כהנים Kohanim don't necessarily need to know
what you need atonement for.
So it's not like a confession, I'm confessing and then I'm giving
this קרבן. korban.
I mean there are certain קרבנות korbanot that you do have וידוי
viduy on, but that's not a general rule for all קרבנות. korbanot.
Right.
So what we're seeing over here is that this
is רצית לבעלים לחובה, ratzit labaalim lechovah, you know,
they're not having, the question is whether it יצא's yotzei technically, you
know.
Right,
יצא yotzei is for the בעל, baal, for the
owner, right.
Okay, so now we're going to bring a challenge, we're going to
bring a ברייתא Baraita that's going to challenge both שמואל Shmuel and
עולא. Ulla. מיתיבי: Meitivei: חטאתו ואשמו עולתו ושלמיו של פלוני עלי, Chatatav
ve'ashamo olato ushlamav shel ploni alai,
if someone pledges,
if someone pledges
to bring the חטאת chatat or the אשם asham or the עולה
olah or the שלמים shelamim of someone else.
And these are קרבנות korbanot basically. Right.
לדעת יצא, Ladaat yatza, if it's with knowledge and consent, the obligation
is fulfilled. שלא לדעת לא יצא, Shelo ladaat lo yatza, but without
knowledge and consent the obligation is not fulfilled. So this the גמרא
Gemara is first assuming that this is applying across the board, both
at the time of designation and at the time of offering,
and therefore this is a challenge to both of them because according
to שמואל Shmuel we said we don't need consent at the time
of offering for the עולה olah and according to עולא Ulla we
don't need consent
at the time of
designation.
So the גמרא Gemara says we can, both of them can interpret
this ברייתא Baraita with no problem. שמואל מוקמי לה
בשעת
הפרשה. Shmuel mokmi lah beshaat hafrashah.
שמואל Shmuel will say that this ברייתא, Baraita, it's not talking about
both, it's specifically talking about the time of הפרשה, hafrashah, the time
of designation, and therefore that's why it says that you need consent.
עולא מוקמי לה בשעת כפרה, Ulla mokmi lah beshaat kapparah, and עולא
Ulla will say this ברייתא Baraita is talking about the time of
כפרה, kapparah, the time when you're actually bringing the offering and that's
why it says you need consent. So
אמר רב פפא: Amar Rav Papa:
מתניתא אהדדי לא
קשיא. Matnita ahadadi lo kashya.
So רב פפא Rav Papa tells us that not only does this
ברייתא Baraita not cause a problem either for שמואל Shmuel or for
עולא, Ulla, but it's also no, for the same reasoning basically, it's
no contradiction with the previous ברייתא. Baraita. The previous ברייתא Baraita that
said that an עולה olah
doesn't need consent and this ברייתא Baraita that says that an עולה
olah does. הא בשעת כפרה הא בשעת
הפרשה. Ha beshaat kapparah, ha beshaat hafrashah.
This one, one of them is talking about the time of consent
and one of them is talking about the time of, sorry, the
time of offering and one of them is talking about the time
of designation. ואמוראי נמי לא
קשיא, Ve'amorai nami lo kashya, and the two אמוראים Amoraim also do
not have any problem with either ברייתא. Baraita. Why? שמואל מוקמי לה
קמייתא בשעת כפרה, Shmuel mokmi lah kammaita beshaat kapparah, שמואל Shmuel would
say the first ברייתא Baraita that says you don't need consent is
talking about the time of offering. בתרייתא בשעת
הפרשה, Batraita beshaat hafrashah, and the later ברייתא Baraita that says you
do need consent is about the time of designation. עולא מוקמי לה
איפכא, Ulla mokmi lah ipcha, and עולא Ulla would do the reverse.
עולא Ulla would say
that the first one that says you don't need consent
is talking about the time of הפרשה, hafrashah, the time of designation,
and the second one that says you do need consent is talking
about the time of כפרה, kapparah, the time of offering. So each
one can make the two ברייתות Baraitot work consistently with each other.
But you know they both agree that the goal isn't just so
the מקדש Mikdash should have the animals because that's not enough. The
person that needs the כפרה kapparah has to know, has to like
agree, has to get כפרה. kapparah.
Right,
that's the second part of the משנה. Mishnah. We have two elements:
one, we can force people because it's a debt, but two, we
can't force them completely because you
have to know about it to sort of agree. So again, so
the goal, the ultimate goal isn't just to give animals to the
מקדש Mikdash without the person having to have some participation. Yeah, right.
And then we say: אמוראי ודאי פליגי, Amorai vadai pligi, but the
two אמוראים, Amoraim, meaning שמואל Shmuel and עולא, Ulla, definitely disagree with
each other. פשיטא. Peshita. גמרא Gemara says of course they disagree with
each other, we've been discussing it as a מחלוקת machloket the whole
time.
So מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, so what would I have thought?
מאי בשעת הפרשה דקאמר שמואל? Mai besha'at hafrasha d'kamar Shmuel? What did
שמואל Shmuel mean when he said that you need
consent at the time of at the time of designation? He meant
אף בשעת הפרשה, af besha'at hafrasha, even at the time of designation,
but you certainly need it at the time of offering and therefore,
well, they're not completely in agreement as תוספות Tosafot points out, they
would still disagree about whether you need...
they're not completely in disagreement.
Right. They would still disagree about whether you need consent at the
time of designation, but at least they are they would at least
they would be in agreement about what the rule is at the
time of offering. And I might have I might have thought this
is what שמואל Shmuel holds, אף על גב דהך קמייתא תיובתיה, af
al gav de'hach kamaita tiyuvtei, even though if that's what he held
the first ברייתא braita would disprove him, קא משמע לן, kamashmalan, he
doesn't hold that way and is not disproven by the ברייתא. braita.
Okay, then we move on to the last bit in the משנה,
mishna, the וכן בגיטי נשים, ve'chen be'gittei nashim, same rule about coercing
until he consents applies to divorces as well.
So אמר רב
ששת, amar Rav Sheshet, האי מאן דמסר מודעא אגיטא מודעיה מודעא. hai
man de'masar moda'a a'gitta, moda'ei moda'a. So a person who makes a
מודעא, moda'a, I'll explain that in a second, on a divorce document,
that מודעא moda'a is valid. So
a מודעא moda'a is anytime you're entering into any contract, if you
if you get two witnesses before before you enter into the contract
and declare in front of the two witnesses the contract I'm about
to enter into is being done under duress,
then then that can invalidate the contract.
So רב ששת Rav Sheshet is essentially saying divorce is a contract
and therefore
the מודעא moda'a works on divorce like any other contract.
So basically if the בית דין beit din כופין אותו עד שיאמר
רוצה אני, kofin oto ad she'yomar rotzeh ani,
if he goes around and says to people...
Well, so we're going to discuss that. How is it a contract
if one party can refuse? The contract could be enforced anyway.
It
it's a contract with special rules that all of מסכת גיטין Masechet
Gittin will discuss that we're not learning right now.
It's not
a contract.
It is, I mean, it's interesting that I mean it's interesting that
in
מסכת גיטין Masechet Gittin you have to go like
20 דף daf in before you get to anything about גיטין. Gittin.
The
first 20 דף daf of גיטין Gittin or more, I don't remember
exactly where the shift happens, is is all about contracts.
And גיטין Gittin is a...
Right.
The first little bit in the משנה mishna and then you get
into contracts and רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, and
you know is it the witnesses or the signing and it it
takes a long time to really get into the גיטין. Gittin. So
you you really see just from the structure of the גמרא Gemara
in גיטין Gittin that it's treating it like a contract with like
you said certain exceptions.
So the גמרא Gemara is so the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא. pshita.
That tells us here also the fact that the גמרא Gemara thinks
it's obvious that a מודעא moda'a would work for גט get means
the גמרא Gemara is treating it as a contract as well.
But a מודעא moda'a meaning I'm not
I didn't mean it when I gave it. Right. You can't say
that after the fact. Before before the fact you have to say
in front of two witnesses I am doing this under duress.
So the בית דין beit din you know forcing me is...
Yes.
Meaning meaning I'm only giving this because someone is forcing me to
give it, I don't really want to give it.
Okay.
So even if the בית דין beit din does that it's still
invalid.
So that's that's what the גמרא Gemara says next to us. So
what so the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, pshita, so לא צריכא. lo
tzricha. So why is this statement necessary? דאנסוה וארצי. de'asoha ve'irtzei. I
might have thought that since he went ahead and actually gave the
גט get that meant he was מבטל, mevatel, he was he intended
to nullify the previous מודעא. moda'a. מהו דתימא ביטולי בטליה, mahu de'teima
bitulei batlei, I might have I might have thought that he is
nullifying the מודעא. moda'a. קא משמע
לן, kamashmalan, so it comes to teach us, what does it come
to teach us? And we're going to see how how this works
in the משנה. mishna. דאם כן ליתני עד שיתן. de'im ken litnei
ad she'yiten. If the act of giving was enough to presume that
you
nullified the מודעא, moda'a,
then the משנה mishna should have simply said כופין אותו עד שיתן.
kofin oto ad she'yiten. We coerce him until he gives the גט.
get. מאי עד שיאמר? mai ad she'yomar? What does it mean we
have we coerce him until he says I want to give it?
עד דמבטלי למודעיה. ad de'mevatlei le'moda'ei. So so giving the גט get
without saying anything is not enough to get rid of these to
get rid of these מודעות, moda'ot, but when you say the words
I want to give it, that's sufficient to nullify any מודעות moda'ot
you might have made before and the גט get and the גט
get and the גט get would be good.
Because otherwise the בית דין beit din כופין kofin would do nothing
because he can always do
a מודעא moda'a beforehand. Exactly. Exactly. Get over.
They do, but there is a...
at least on the books.
Sometimes after the גט get is given. Right.
Which is why a good בית דין beit din doesn't shouldn't let
you keep the גט. get.
Except there is no good בית דין, beit din, so
let's...
I know many rabbis on בתי דין batte din who are, you
may not like the הלכה halacha they have to work with, but
who are really working their hardest.
And as תוספות Tosafot points out, this גמרא Gemara is actually the
source of the custom of ביטול מודעות, bittul moda'ot, which is
when you're giving a גט, get, the first thing בית דין Beit
Din does is ask you to explicitly nullify any מודעות, moda'ot, any
statement you might have previously made to the effect that you're doing
this under duress.
And more than that, you say, and I will never put an
ערעור irur on the גט get ever, right before giving it.
Right, that's all part of it. And then we also, the בית
דין Beit Din also is מתיר matir any נדר neder that they
might have made that would have prevented the גט get from being
חל.
chal. Yeah, ביטול מכאן ולהבא, bitul mikan u-le-haba, you know, מודעות, moda'ot,
you have that also in חושן משפט. Choshen Mishpat. They never put
a what? What's the word?
An ערעור. irur. You never put a דעת. da'at. After the גט
get is given, then sometimes a man will say, had I known
that giving the גט get meant I had to move out of
my house or whatever, I had a case like that actually, where
the בית דין Beit Din said, okay, גט get is good.
So this is a condition, that's the word that you used?
ערעור irur or דעת. da'at.
It's
like you make a contention.
You contest it. At the time of the giving of the גט,
get, the party states, I will never put a doubt that this
is a כשר kosher גט. get. And the woman also has to
say, I'll never claim that I didn't receive the גט get or
whatever that it wasn't good.
They have to say that in
order to, they're given a script. They're handed a script that they
recite.
All right, so הדרן עלך אומר משקל. hadran alach omer mishkal. So
that's the end of our פרק. perek. We'll start a new פרק
perek
now. So new פרק perek is שום היתומים. shum ha-yetomim. We're now
talking about, I don't know what this has anything to do with
מסכת ערכין.
Masechet Arachin. Because you talked about the collateralizing, maybe that's why.
I guess, I guess it's connected in that sense. Once we're talking
about collateral, we'll talk about other
collateral.
So שום היתומים. shum ha-yetomim. So if we have to,
if a father dies and has A, land, and B, outstanding debts,
and he only,
and he leaves children under בר מצווה, bar mitzvah, so then the
בית דין Beit Din will come and sell the property of the
inheritance in order to pay the father's debts. So that's שום היתומים.
shum ha-yetomim. How do we evaluate the price or sell the property
of the orphans in order to pay the father's debts? So the
משנה Mishnah says it's a period of שלושים יום, shloshim yom, 30
days.
The גמרא Gemara will flesh it out more, but basically what happens
is the בית דין Beit Din first assesses how much they think
the land is worth, and then they
basically, that becomes the starting bid, and then you have 30 days,
and over the course of 30 days, whoever offers the most money
buys the
land.
Whatever money is collected goes to the person
who is owed the debt. If it's, I presume if it's more
than the debt, then it would go back to the orphans, though
I don't know how often that ever happens.
Would it be different than anything else? Like let's say
הקדש hekdesh or something, בדק הבית, bedek ha-bayit, they want to sell
it and use the proceeds, wouldn't they do the same thing?
Right. So the first תוספות Tosafot in this פרק perek asks that
question. It says, wait a second, this is the same procedure for
any time the בית דין Beit Din have to sell someone's land
to pay their debt. And
תוספות Tosafot basically answers that
the משנה Mishnah tells us about orphans specifically because I might have
thought that orphans should, you should give a longer amount of time
for orphans to raise the bids even higher for, you know, to
get extra money to help the orphans, but קא משמע לן kamashma
lan that it's treated like any other debt. The only exception being
משום ההקדש שישים יום. mishum ha-hekdesh shishim yom. However, when
you've donated your land to הקדש hekdesh and the בית דין Beit
Din has to sell it to, or the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
has to sell it to,
because they don't want land, so to collect money for the treasury,
so then we give an auction period of 60 days. ומכריזין בבוקר
ובערב. u-machrizin ba-boker u-va-erev.
And we announce it over the course of the 30 days or
the 60 days every morning and every evening.
And
is there any concern for the orphans, think about withholding some funds
for the orphans for their needs before what amount they're going to
sell to fulfill the obligation to the person who was owed
money?
I presume so. We do have systems in place to
make... All right, so the
גמרא Gemara asks
מאי שנא בבוקר ובערב? Mai shna baboker uva'erev? So why specifically in
morning and evening do we make this announcement that we're selling the
land?
Why now? When else is it, lunchtime?
Yeah, I mean,
noon, midnight, more
exposure, more exposure, different types of people.
Yeah, we even have like a morning and evening papers, same idea.
Right. So אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda
Amar Rav,
so רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says in the name of רב, Rav,
בשעת הוצאת פועלים ובשעת הכנסת פועלים. bish'at hotza'at po'alim uvish'at hachnasat po'alim.
We announce it at the time when people are leaving from work
and at the time when people are going to work. Exactly, it's
rush hour. That's when people are around, so that's when we announce
it. Of course, the גמרא Gemara is going to give a different
explanation. דאיכא דניחא ליה למזבן, de'ika denicha lei lemizban, אמר להו לפועלים,
amar lehu lepo'alim, אזילו סיירו לי
ארעא.
azilu sayeru li
ar'a.
What? So why do we announce it when people are going home
from work? So that way
the wealthy people who are the ones most of the workers are
working for, who are also the ones who can afford to buy
the land, they can tell their workers as they're going home, either
leave a little bit early or I'll pay you a little overtime
or whatever it is, and go check out this land for me
and tell me if you think it's a good deal. בשעת הכנסת
פועלים, bish'at hachnasat po'alim,
so then why do we do it again in the morning at
the time they're going to work?
הכנסה hachnasa is when they're going back, no?
The other way
around.
הכנסה hachnasa is when they're going home, no? Wouldn't you have thought
about it that way?
הוצאה hotza'a is to leave, הוצאת הפועלים, hotza'at hapo'alim, right.
הכנסה hachnasa is entering. And yeah, if you look at if you
look at רבנו גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom,
that's how he explains it
also. It's הוצאה, hotza'a, it's a little awkward because it's reversing the
order of the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah said morning and evening
and now we're talking evening and morning. But in terms of
in terms of, and I think תוספות Tosafot explains it that same
way also if you read the little תוספות, Tosafot, but
in terms of the flow of the rest of the סוגיא, sugya,
it makes much more sense if we say this is evening.
Okay, so הוצאה hotza'a is evening you're saying?
Yeah, הוצאה hotza'a is when they're leaving work because now that's when
when they're leaving
work
is when
when the boss can tell them, as you're as you're going home,
check out this property for me. Right,
no,
that's what I said. Either he could tell them, he'll obviously pay
them for their time. They're not obligated to, they're not slaves, they're
not obligated to work when they're not being paid. So either he'll
let them leave early to do it or he'll pay them overtime,
I don't know exactly how it's going to work, but yeah, during
the time when they are being paid for their service. ובשעת הכנסת
פועלים, uvish'at hachnasat po'alim, at the time that the workers are coming
into work. So why do we announce it then? דנידכר, denidkar, דאמר
להו. de'amar lehu.
So that way the boss will remember that he had asked the
workers to
check out the land. ניזיל ונישיילינהו, nizil venishaylinhu, and therefore they'll go
and ask the workers what they thought about the land
and they'll remember to go and buy it. תניא נמי הכי, tanya
nami hachi, we have a ברייתא Baraita that teaches this way also.
שום היתומים שלושים יום, shum hayetomim shloshim yom, ושום ההקדש שישים יום.
veshum hahekdesh shishim yom. So that's the same as the משנה. Mishnah.
The auction period to sell the property of orphans is thirty days
and to sell land for הקדש hekdesh is sixty days. ומכריזין בבוקר
ובערב, umachrizin baboker uva'erev, and we announce every morning and every evening.
בשעת הוצאת פועלים ובשעת הכנסת פועלים, bish'at hotza'at po'alim uvish'at hachnasat po'alim,
at the time that the workers leave and at the time that
the workers come in. So what do we... now the ברייתא Baraita
is going to go on to tell us what is it exactly
we announce. שדה פלוני בסימניה ובמצריה, sadeh ploni besimaneha uvimetzareha,
this field, and we give its סימנים, simanim, identifying markers, and its
מצרים, metzarim, its borders, so people know exactly what's being sold. כך
היא יפה וכך היא שומה. kach hi yafah vekach hi shumah.
This is how good it is and this is what it's
worth.
יפה yafah would be more like descriptive, like it's a beautiful field?
Right, so רש"י Rashi says יפה yafah is
כך וכך היא עושה תבואה. kach vekach hi osah tevuah. This is
how much grain you can expect it to produce per year. Right,
like what quality field is it? וכך היא שומה vekach hi shumah
is the price that the בית דין beit din has...
Isn't that interesting? You might have thought like to say the opposite.
Like you know, you would have set a price and that way
people can like sort of maybe potentially come up with some... Let's
say I would have thought it'd be worth ten thousand dollars, the
בית דין beit din says it's worth a thousand dollars, and now
I'm going to lower my bid.
Right, I mean every auction has an opening bid though.
Not necessarily, you know, it depends. Like there may be like a
whisper number of some sort, but this you don't necessarily publicize it,
you know, it really depends.
Well, this one does anyway.
Is this an auction or a sale? It's an
auction. Uh-huh. Yeah. Yeah.
And so קרקע
יפה
karka
yafa is is what kind of land is it? Is it expected
how much grain is it expected to produce? The קרקע שומה karka
shuma and it that's the value the בית דין Beis Din evaluated
it as, which is the opening bid. And if people are if
people are playing rationally, whatever it's actually worth is what the bidding
should get up to anyway. Not that people always play rationally.
So then we say כל הרוצה ליקח, kol harotzeh likach, so anyone
who wants...
Just wait, why does it say, sorry, so let's say, you know,
it's worth a thousand dollars. Then I come in like right away,
say, okay, come on, a thousand dollars. So we're still going to
wait? Yeah, we wait till the thirty days comes to an end
and then just say, oh, well, he already I already bid a
thousand dollars, so if you want to get it from him, you
got to bid more? Yeah. Is that that's what they'll say?
Okay. We have we start we start with the price the בית
דין Beis Din evaluates it at and then people can bid it
up over thirty days.
Right, no, but presumably the first person at a particular bid, assuming
that he's not outbid, would get it.
Yes.
Okay. No, you can't lower. I mean, if nobody bids, I guess
maybe they would lower it, but no. The גמרא Gemara doesn't give
us any provision for lowering it. So כל הרוצה ליקח יבוא ויקח
על מנת ליתן לאשה בכתובתה ולבעל חוב בחובו. kol harotzeh likach yavo
v'yikach al menat litein l'isha b'ktubata u'l'ba'al chov b'chovo. So we say
anyone who anyone who wants to buy should come and buy it
in order to give the money to the wife or to the
widow for her כתובה. ktuba. So
when the husband died, if he was married, so then the his
his wife, his widow is entitled to her כתובה ktuba payment. So
one of the debts we could be selling the land for is
to pay is to pay her כתובה. ktuba. ולבעל חוב בחובו u'l'ba'al
chov b'chovo or to another creditor for for his debt.
Why do they have to say that?
That's the גמרא's Gemara question. למה לי למימר על מנת ליתן לאשה
כתובתה ולבעל חוב חובו? lama li l'meimar al menat litein l'isha ktubata
u'l'ba'al chov chovo? So why do we have to, the גמרא Gemara
asks, why do we have to say in order to give the
money to the widow for her כתובה ktuba or to a creditor
for his debt? So the גמרא's Gemara going to tell us there's
actually there's actually reasons why people would prefer one or the other
and are more likely to bid depending on who it's going to.
דאיכא דניחא ליה בבעל חוב דמיקל בזוזי. d'ika d'nicha lei b'ba'al chov
d'meikel b'zuzei.
So the בעל חוב ba'al chov is a is a creditor, he's
some kind of professional merchant. And professional merchants, we assume, are are
experts on what's a good coin and what's a bad coin. Remember
in those days in those days, you know, as a coin got
worn off and it had less less metal in it, the coin
was actually worth less and it would reach a point where people
would start would stop taking it as its full value. So we
assume a professional merchant is an expert on is an expert on
what's a good coin and what's a bad coin
and therefore they're going to have a and therefore they're going to
have a less exacting standard of what they'll accept than an ordinary
person. We're assuming the widow here is not a professional merchant. Than
an ordinary person who is going to want something that looks better
because they're not sure exactly what's going to be accepted. So they're
going to be stricter on what they'll accept. So there are some
people that would specifically
that would specifically want to buy it from the creditor, דמיקל בזוזי,
d'meikel b'zuzei, because because
he's lenient on which coins he will accept and therefore it's their
chance to get rid of all their old coins that nobody else
wants to take. ואיכא דניחא ליה
באשה,
v'ika d'nicha
lei b'isha, and there are some people who would rather give
the money to to the widow, דשקלה על יד על יד, d'shakla
al yad al yad, because
widows are, and this was just the reality in their time I
guess, were often willing to take it in installment. על יד על
יד al yad al yad means a little bit at a time.
And so maybe you can't afford the full amount at once, but
if you're buying it from a widow, again, she has to consent
to it as well, she's entitled to get it all at once
if she wants,
but apparently it was the case that widows often were willing to
take it in installments. And so if you don't have the money
to pay it all at once and you want to pay in
installments, then you're more likely to go and bid if you know
that it that the money is going to the כתובה ktuba of
the widow.
Okay, and I think we'll stop here.